<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon preached before the Right Honourable the Lord Mayor, and aldermen of London, at Guild-Hall Chappel by William Pindar ...</title>
            <author>Pindar, William, 1644 or 5-1678.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 55KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 24 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A54894</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12560915</idno>
  <idno type="VID">63166</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2240987856</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing P2251</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R18911</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">12560915</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A54894)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 63166)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 701:24)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon preached before the Right Honourable the Lord Mayor, and aldermen of London, at Guild-Hall Chappel by William Pindar ...</title>
                  <author>Pindar, William, 1644 or 5-1678.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 40 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Henry Brome ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1677.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Running title: A sermon preached upon Prov. xvii. v. 27.</note>
                  <note>Errata: p. 40.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Duke University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="uniform_title">Bible. --  O.T. --  Proverbs XVII, 27 --  Sermons.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2014-06 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-10 </date>
            <label>Alexis (Ali) Jakobson </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-10 </date>
            <label>Alexis (Ali) Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:63166:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:63166:1"/>
            <p>A SERMON Preached before the RIGHT HONOURABLE. THE Lord Mayor; AND Aldermen of London; AT <hi>GUILD-HALL CHAPPEL.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By <hi>William Pindar;</hi> Chaplain to the Right Honourable. <hi>Ford</hi> Lord <hi>Grey</hi> of <hi>Werke,</hi> and Fellow of <hi>Ʋniversity Colledg<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> in <hi>OXFORD.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON;</hi> Printed for <hi>Henry Brome</hi> at the <hi>Gun</hi> near the West-End of <hi>St. Pauls Church-Yard.</hi> 1677.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="order_to_print">
            <pb facs="tcp:63166:2"/>
            <head>Davies Mayor.</head>
            <opener>
               <dateline>
                  <date>Martis XXVII. <hi>die</hi> Martii 1677. <hi>Anno{que} Regni Regis</hi> Caroli <hi>Secundi,</hi> Angliae; <hi>&amp;c.</hi> XXIX.</date>
               </dateline>
            </opener>
            <p>THis Court doth desire Mr. <hi>Pindar</hi> to Print his Sermon Preached at the <hi>Guild-Hall Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel</hi> on the 25th day of this instant <hi>March,</hi> before the <hi>Lord Mayor</hi> and <hi>Aldermen</hi> of this City.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Wagstaffe</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="imprimatur">
            <p>Imprimatur;</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <date>April. 11. 1677.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Guili Jane.</hi> R.P.D. <hi>Hen. Episc. Lond.</hi> a Sacr. domesticis.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:63166:2"/>
            <head>TO The Right Honourable. Sir. <hi>THOMAS DAVIES.</hi> LORD MAYOR. OF LONDON; And to the COURT of ALDERMEN.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Right Honourable;</salute>
            </opener>
            <p n="1">
               <hi>I</hi> Did not design that the following Sermon should have been other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise publick than from the Pulpit; but since you have been pleased to think it worthy of being so from the Press, I humbly recommend it to your Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tronage;
<pb facs="tcp:63166:3"/>and have no more to do, but to beseech Almighty God, that it may prosper in the work whereunto it is sent, and that every one that shall read it, may reap some benefit by it. Which is the hearty desire of.</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Right Honourable,</salute>
               <signed>Your most humble Servant, <hi>William Pindar.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:63166:3"/>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>PROV. xvij.</hi> v. <hi>27.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <q>A man of Ʋn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstanding is of an excellent spirit.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hat all true Knowledge does very much enlarge all the Faculties of the Soul, and enable them to perform their several Fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions with greater readi- and vivacity, is evident from the nature of <hi>Truth,</hi> whose property it is to <hi>make us Free,</hi> to deliver our Minds from the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumbrances of Ignorance and Errour, to raise them from that vale of darkness and misery wherein they would otherwise lie grove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, and to endue us with true amplitude and ingenuity of spirit. And hence it came to pass, that some men who had no other con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct but the light of Nature, whose Employ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment it was to seek after <hi>Wisdom,</hi> were many of them Men of such raised capacities, and every way so fitted to serve their generati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; that they kept the World from being
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:63166:4"/>over-run with Barbarisme and stupidity; and by cultivating of Arts, establishing So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cieties, and enlarging of Commerce and Conversation, did sweeten the tempers of Mankind, made them become more service<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to one another, and in some measure answer the ends of their Creation. It was Wisdom and Knowledge which made them the blessing and security, as well as the glory of their several Ages; this which enrolled their Names in the <hi>Annals</hi> of their Countries, and makes the World in after-Ages, have more than ordinary Kindness for their Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mories. And indeed not without reason, since it is Wisdom and Understanding that makes one man much more useful, and so more va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luable than another; without which, the great things of this World, <hi>Birth,</hi> and <hi>Wealth,</hi> and <hi>Honour,</hi> cannot give any great matter of Commendation; it is Wisdom alone which makes these things become Illustri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, this which gives the preheminence, that ennobles and advances our Nature, <hi>that is more precious than Rubies, and all the things that you can desire, are not to be compared unto her.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And this is in some measure true of that Wisdom and Knowledge which fits a man
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:63166:4"/>for the prudent management of the affairs of this life. Which gives him an insight into the Natures of Things, and Consequences of Actions; which makes a man an able <hi>Poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tician,</hi> or an acute <hi>Naturalist;</hi> which acquaints him with the <hi>Nature, Humours,</hi> and <hi>Passions</hi> of Mankind; enables him to apply himself properly to them, and so to manage them, as to make their contrary studies, inclinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and affections, joyntly conspire to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance the Common good.</p>
            <p>But it is in a far more eminent sense true of that Divine Wisdom which the King of <hi>Israel</hi> so much recommends to us in this Book of <hi>Proverbs;</hi> the Excellency and Usefulness whereof he had found out both by deep consideration, and by trial and practice. Therefore does he Exhort us, <hi>in all our getting, to get Understanding; for Wisedom is the princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pal thing,</hi> that which we are to lay as the foundation of our happiness; that <hi>she shall bring thee to Honour when thou dost embrace her, she shall give to thine head an ornament of Grace, and encompass thee with a Crown of Glory.</hi> That therefore <hi>Blessed is the man that heareth her, watching daily at her gates;</hi> For, <hi>If thou be thus wise, thou shalt be wise for thy self.</hi> This
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:63166:5"/>will establish thy heart in that which is good, will refine thy spirit, and raise thy Mind above the delights and satisfactions of the Men of the World. This will give thee other pleasures than they are acquainted with, and will minister Comforts which they cannot receive. This will be the constant guide and security of all thy wayes, and will preserve thee from falling into the snares of Sin and Misery; <hi>For he that walketh uprightly, walketh surely; the Law of the wise is the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain of life; and a man of Understanding is of an Excellent spirit.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And here in the first place it may not be amiss to observe, That there is a different reading of these words set down in the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent of our Bible, where that which in the <hi>Text</hi> is called <hi>an excellent spirit,</hi> is in the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent, a <hi>cool spirit, i. e.</hi> a spirit not easily provo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked, such as is long-suffering and patient, not quick in resenting injuries; in the <hi>Septuagint,</hi>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>; a sedate and calm temper of mind, that is not apt to fly out upon any provoca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion into rage and passion. And this read<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing suits well with the foregoing part of the <hi>Verse, He that hath knowledge, spareth his words, i. e.</hi> a wise man <hi>is slow to speak,</hi> as St. <hi>James,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:63166:5"/>c.</hi> 1.19. expresseth it; is wary and delibe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate in his talk; in opposition to profuse and impertinent babling in Common Conversa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, to vain boasting and vaunting ones self, to Blabbing of Secrets, and to being prone to anger and impatience. Thus <hi>he that hath knowledge, spareth his words,</hi> is <hi>slow to speak;</hi> and a man of Understanding is of a <hi>cool spirit,</hi> is also <hi>slow to wrath.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But indeed the whole sense of the <hi>Text</hi> cannot be comprehended in that narrow no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, as our Translation shews, and some <hi>Critiques</hi> have observed upon it; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I shall consider it in its fullest Latitude, and consequently the Marginal sense will be taken in, in my handling of it. Which I shall do by endeavouring to clear these things:</p>
            <p n="1">1. Who is this Man of Understanding, what kind of Wisdom is it that denominates him, and upon what grounds he is called a <hi>wise man.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. What this <hi>Excellency of spirit</hi> is, and what are those things especially that manifest it.</p>
            <p n="3">3. How this Wisdom contributes to the ennobling of the Mind, so as to make a man
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:63166:6"/>in whom it resides, be emphatically cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led one of an <hi>Excellent spirit.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. Who is this Man of Understanding, what kind of Wisdom, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now by Understanding and Wisdom, all along this Book, as in most places of Holy Scripture, is meant the sincere practise of true Religion, Fearing of God, and keeping his Commandements. To honour, and to serve, and to love God, to believe in him, and to rely upon him, to acknowledge him in all our wayes, to make our Prayer always before him, and to behave our selves so as always under his all-seeing eye; to do unto others so as we our selves would be done unto; to govern our natural appetites ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the dictates of Reason and Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, to make all our passions instruments of righteousness, and to perform those duties in our several relations which God, and Man expect from us, and so as to adorn the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of <hi>Jesus Christ</hi> in all things; these are the instances of that Divine Wisdom which the Holy Scripture recommends unto us; and all that Understanding, Prudence, and Policy, which does not manifest it self in such works as these, is <hi>foolishness with God.</hi> And to
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:63166:6"/>walk contrary to God in those revelations of his Will which he has made known unto us, to live without any consideration of his Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, or Providence; For a weak and infirm Creature to behave himself so, as owning no dependance that he has upon the Almighty; to provoke Him to anger, who can with the meanest word of his Mouth, destroy and ruine us for ever; to bring upon our selves several Diseases by an immoderate indulging of our appetites; to lay in matter for future repentance, by now walking after the Lusts of the Flesh; to run the certain hazard of undergoing the greatest Miseries that can befal humane nature, for the short pleasures of sin; These are the instances of the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>test <hi>madness and folly</hi> that any man can possi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly be guilty of; and to do thus, is the cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter of one that hates Knowledge, of one that is a Fool, and has no Understanding. For in the issue of things, he will be found the onely wise man, that Fears the Lord, and that departs from evil. Now that the Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous and Religious man is really a man of Understanding, and upon what account he is so, will appear by considering these <hi>Two</hi> things:</p>
            <p n="1">
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:63166:7"/>1. Because he understands, and pursues steadily, that which is his truest interest, and makes all other things give way to it.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Because he governs himself Commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dably in that Station and Capacity which he possesses in the World, and in those variety of Accidents which befall him in it. Now he that has made choice of the best End, and uses all suitable means to obtain it; that go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verns his affairs discreetly, and behaves him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>felf so in all conditions, as to gain Credit to himself, and his profession, may well be sty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led an <hi>Understanding Man.</hi> But thus a Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous and Religious Man does; For</p>
            <p n="1">1. He understands, and pursues steadily that which is his truest interest, and makes all other things give way to it.</p>
            <p>For if it be possible that all those great things which are talked concerning Immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tality, and a Future Life should be true; If there may be indeed a God that governs the World, that has placed man in it, in a state capable of receiving much advancement, If he observe those Laws which he has given to him; If this God may bring us all to Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and may reward or punish us, accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing as we shall have spent our lives here; If
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:63166:7"/>these Rewards and Punishments may chance to prove Eternal, and to answer that cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter which has been given of them; then the Religious man who lives so as if these things really were to come to pass, does in so doing pursue his truest interest; because there is so little proportion betwixt the things of this life, and those which are said to concern the other; those things if they should be, will so infinitely transcend all our affairs here; that these cannot be our inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rest when they are put in the ballance against those; and he cannot be a wise man, that would not take some pains and care to secure the falling out of such a chance.</p>
            <p>But now if those things be very probable, and there be very great likelihood that the Soul shall prove Immortal, and live for ever, either in endless Joyes, or Miseries, and that according to its works here; If it be ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry unlikely that the Sinner who has lived <hi>without God in the World,</hi> without all sense of his Providence, of his Holiness, of his Justice, should at last escape the Divine Vengeance, and that his sins should not at last find him out; If it be probable, that the fruits of his doings shall be at last given to him, whilest
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:63166:8"/>the Righteous shall be for ever happy in the enjoyment of the Love and Mercy of God, whom he faithfully served here: then does the Pious Man pursue indeed his truest in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terest, and upon better grounds then they do who venture some part of their Estates in Merchandise, and by way of Trade to bring in more; in as much as if the Pious man's hopes succeed, of which there is as great a probability as there can be, it will more abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dantly requite him: and if they should not, yet his loss would be very inconsiderable; and he that will not run the hazard of a small loss, supposing that some hazard were to be run, to gain a return ten thousand times exceeding his venture, runs counter to all the wisdom and providence of this world, and indeed is a most unfit man to live, and thrive in it.</p>
            <p>But now lastly, If after all this prove very <hi>Certain, If verily there be a reward for the Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous, and doubtless a God that judgeth in the earth;</hi> If God will certainly <hi>render tribulation and anguish upon every Soul of Man that doth evil, but glory, honour, and peace to every man that worketh good;</hi> If we shall as certainly die, as we do now live; and as certainly after death
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:63166:8"/>be brought to Judgment, and receive the things that we have done in the body, as that we shall die; If such shall be our portion in that Future Eternal state to which we are all hasting, as we have chosen here: And if we have as great proof and evidence of these things, as the nature of them will admit, and any reasonable man would desire to have; If the wisest part of all Mankind in all Ages of the World, have not been cheated, and abused, and mad, when they did believe them, made Laws, administred Justice, and governed the World thereafter; If we may trust the Testimonies of our own Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sciences, and every man's heart when it gives him secret warnings of them, has not put a trick upon us, and to no purpose falsly alar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med us, when there was nothing but sha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow to disturb us; If God himself who can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not lie, has not born witness to a Falshood, when he has at sundry times, and in divers manners, ascertained these things to the World; If the Testimony of one that came to us from the dead, even of our Lord who brought <hi>Life and Immortality to light,</hi> may be thought convincing; If the Word of God, the Bloud of Martyrs, the Profession of the
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:63166:9"/>Church, or the Belief of the World, can make this Truth evident beyond all rational contradiction, as without controversie they do: Then is it equally evident, that the Religious man who governs his life accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to these principles, must needs by so do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing pursue his truest interest. For if these things certainly be, which you see we have all the reason in the world to believe, it must be more a man's interest to secure his own Soul, then it could be to gain the whole world; all the most desireable things of this present life, will not ballance the loss of the Soul, <hi>For what shall it profit a man, If he shall gain the whole World, and lose his own Soul? or what shall a man give in exchange for his Soul?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And therefore, the Pious Man who makes all the things of this World give way to this Great Interest; who prefers this in his choice, and takes care first to secure this, and what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever may become of his temporal affairs, is resolved not to lose himself eternally; This man who is thus wise for himself, in things of infinitely great moment: must needs be a wise and understanding man.</p>
            <p n="2">2. He is so, because he governs himself
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:63166:9"/>Commendably in that station and capacity which he possesses in the World, and in those Accidents which may befall him in it.</p>
            <p>By which is not meant, that a Virtuous man may be never guilty of any indiscre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions; or that he is always able to manage his affairs so dextrously in the World, as to be look't upon by others as a shrewd man, and one that has more than an ordinary in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sight into things: but this is understood, namely, that making that allowance for mens natural tempers, and parts, and way of Education, their Converse, and way of Living in the world, and several such things, upon which the variety of mens abilities for business must depend; a Virtuous man shall certainly out-strip him that is not so, in the true management of those affairs which Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence shall call him unto; and whatso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever the issues of his labours are, shall more adorn that station which he posseffes in the World. For he that lives under a constant sense of God's Providence, that knows that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e <hi>is not placed in the World at all adventure,</hi> as the Atheist foolishly thought, <hi>Wisdome</hi> 2. But that God has determined the bounds of our habitation; that he has ordered every man
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:63166:10"/>his Province, and what labour and work he should be busied about until the Evening, <hi>till the Night comes wherein no man can work;</hi> He that knows very well that God governs the World wisely, and according to his own good pleasure; that the success of all our actions proceeds from his blessing alone, and that therefore lives in a constant dependance upon this Wise Disposer of all things, and in an entire resignation of himself, and his af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs to his good Providence; he that studies to be quiet, and to do his own business, and meddles not with those things which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>speak men busie-bodies in other mens mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters: In a word, he that has <hi>learned in what state soever he is, therewith to be content,</hi> is fit to live Commendably in any estate, for pos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sessing an even and equal temper of Mind, he will live humbly, thankfully, and watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully, and so make every condition become advantageous to him.</p>
            <p>If he be in Authority, he considers by whose hand he was placed there, for what End he was raised above his Brethren, he will study to promote the Publick good, governing such as are committed to his Charge in the Fear of God, always remembring that account
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:63166:10"/>which he must make. If he be an inferiour, he learns the duty of submission and obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience, <hi>with good will doing service, as to the Lord, and not unto men, so doing the Will of God from the heart, by being subject, not onely for wrath, but also for Conscience sake.</hi> If he be a Master, he behaves himself towards his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendants with that sweetness and good will, so as to make the yoke easie and pleasant to them, <hi>knowing that his Master also is in heaven, and that there is no respect of persons with him:</hi> And if he be a Servant, he makes Conscience of doing his Masters business, <hi>not with eye<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>service, as men-pleasers, but in singleness of heart, Fearing God.</hi> If he have Children, they he knows are given to him that he may bring them up in the nurture and admonition of the Lord; are they taken from him? then he knows they are returned unto him that gave them.</p>
            <p>Has he an affluence of all the good things of this World? then he looks up with thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulness to the Soveraign Disposer of all things, from whose Bounty he has received them all; and he considers himself as the Steward of these manifold Gifts of God; and therefore takes care to dispence them prudent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:63166:11"/>to the honour of the Supream Lord; Piously, to the necessities of his Brethren; and so by his bountifulness causeth many thanksgivings unto God. He makes to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self Friends of the perishing substance, that he may have his share in the Immortal Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches; and how large soever his Possessions may be on Earth, yet his Country, his Heart, his Conversation is in Heaven.</p>
            <p>Does Poverty, or other Calamities afflict him? The<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> he knows <hi>do not spring out of the ground,</hi> but are sent and managed by the Conduct of the Almighty. By these there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he is corrected, and humbled; instruct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and improved. His Mind, which must sustain him under any difficulties, is it self supported by the Divine Assistances, and the constant chearfulness of a good Conscience; whose Comforts will refresh his Soul, <hi>when the Fields shall yield no meat, and the Flock shall be cut off from the Fold.</hi> Hab. 3.17.</p>
            <p>In a word, whatsoever condition that is which is the Effect of God's Will, is also the Object of his own Choice, he desires to be none other thing in this World than his good Providence shall be pleased to make him; therefore he can with Patience have his ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectations
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:63166:12"/>frustrated, he can take any dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>appointment in what he most affects; and tho he knows it to be his duty, to use all lawful means to preserve to himself, and his dependants, the comforts of this life; yet when that's done, he wisely resigns himself to the Sovereign Will of God, and dares not contest with him, whose Will we may not, we cannot indeed resist. To this height of Mind was St. <hi>Paul</hi> arrived, with such an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent spirit was he endued, <hi>Phil.</hi> 4.12. <hi>I know both how to be abased, and how to abound; every where, and in all things, I am instructed, both to be full, and to be hungry; both to abound, and to suffer need.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And a man thus well prepared for all the contingencies of humane life, and that can thus well govern himself in any condition wherein he may be placed, as the Virtuous and Religious Man you see can do, must needs be a Wise and Understanding man.</p>
            <p n="2">2. I come now to speak to the Second Particular, wherein I proposed to shew, what this Excellency of spirit is, and what are those things especially that manifest it.</p>
            <pb n="18" facs="tcp:63166:13"/>
            <p>Now for a spirit to be <hi>Excellent,</hi> is to be endued with that Divine Temper of Mind, and all those Perfections which are apt to excite our <hi>Love,</hi> and our <hi>Admiration,</hi> and our <hi>Praise.</hi> To have all those Qualifications which we cannot but Honour, and highly Esteem; For <hi>Honour is an acknowledgment of anothers excellency.</hi> As on the other hand, <hi>base<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness</hi> and <hi>sordidness</hi> of Spirit is apt to beget our hatred, and contempt. And then we ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count the mind <hi>base</hi> and sordid, when it has contracted such Evil habits, as make a Man unfit for society; when it is cruel, or proud, or malicious, when it isperfidious, or Coward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, or superstitious; when it is sunk down in sense, and become <hi>Earthly, Sensual, Devi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lish.</hi> But that wisdom which gives this ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellency of Spirit, <hi>is first pure, then peaceable, gentle, and easie to be intreated, full of Mercy and good fruits, without partiality, and without hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crisie.</hi> James 3.17.</p>
            <p>Now this greatness and <hi>Excellency</hi> of Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, which it is a piece of natural justice in us to love and Honour, manifests it self chief<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in these following things.</p>
            <p n="1">1. In a resolute performance of our duty,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:63166:13"/>notwithstanding the dangers that it may ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose us unto.</p>
            <p n="2">2. In a patient and magnanimous bearing of those afflictions, or calamities which may befal us.</p>
            <p n="3">3. In a valiant resisting all those gay Temptations of the World, which are de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>signed to draw us into Sin.</p>
            <p n="4">4. In being willing and ready to Forgive our Enemies.</p>
            <p n="5">5. In delighting in an universal Benefi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cence, in doing good unto all Men.</p>
            <p>These are the things which discover the true greatness and Excellency of the wise Mans Spirit.</p>
            <p n="1">1. A resolute performance of our duty, notwithstanding the dangers which it may expose us unto.</p>
            <p>For <hi>Daniel</hi> to make his dayly Prayers to the God of Heaven and Earth, by whose special Providence he had been raised above all the Princes of <hi>Persia,</hi> when there was no Decree of the King against it, nor could he run any hazard by such Devotions, was no more than might be expected from every <hi>Israelite:</hi> But to do it when the Decree was Sealed accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the Law of the <hi>Medes</hi> and <hi>Persians,</hi> that
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:63166:14"/>
               <hi>he should ask no Petition save onely of the King;</hi> not to intermit the doing of his duty onely for <hi>Thirty dayes,</hi> so to have wisely complyed with the Law, which he knew was purpose<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly contrived against himself, that so he might out-wit his Enemies; and by caution and prudent yielding make their folly in the end, more conspicuous than their malice was in the beginning: But when he knew that <hi>they had bent their Bow, and made ready their Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rows to shoot at him that was upright in heart;</hi> when the writing was signed, then to go in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to his house, <hi>open his windows, pray three times a day to his God as afore-time,</hi> tho the next Prayer he was to make, might be in the <hi>Den of Lions;</hi> was an argument that he deserved all that character which <hi>Belshazzar's Queen</hi> had given of him, namely, <hi>that light, and wis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, and understanding, and an excellent spirit was found in him,</hi> Dan. 5.11, 12.</p>
            <p>The like greatness of spirit was it that animated the three <hi>Jewes,</hi> which were set over the Affairs of the Province of <hi>Babylon, Dan.</hi> 3. See but with what bravery they answered <hi>Nebuchadnezzar,</hi> when he required them to fall down and worship his <hi>golden Image;</hi> and in case they refused, were to be
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:63166:14"/>cast the same hour into the mid'st of a <hi>burn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing fiery Furnace; We are not careful to answer thee,</hi> say they, <hi>in this matter; If it be so, our God whom we serve is able to deliver us, and he will deliver us; But if not, be it known unto thee, that we will not serve thy gods.</hi> We know our Duty, and are resolved to practise it, what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soever the issue of it shall be: Our God, we are sure, is able to deliver us, &amp; we trust that he will do so; but that we leave to his Wis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom: For tho we were sure that he would not deliver us, yet we need no time to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liberate what is best for us to do; we come provided with an answer, and with a resolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, <hi>for we must worship the Lord our God, and him onely must we serve, therefore we will not worship thy gods.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This was that wisdom, and spirit, with which our Lord endued his Apostles, and fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nished them for the work of the Ministry whereunto he had appointed them, which all their Adversaries were not able to gain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>say, nor resist. By this they durst appeal unto the <hi>Sanhedrim</hi> it self whether they could be dispensed with, for waving their duty, <hi>Whether it be right in the sight of God, to hearken unto you more than unto God, judge ye.</hi> They en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:63166:15"/>their Protestation with boldness, what they designed to do for the future, <hi>For we can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not</hi> (say they) <hi>but speak the things which we have seen, and heard;</hi> and this made them <hi>depart from the presence of the Council with joy, that they were counted worthy to suffer shame for the Name of Christ.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And tho the Apostles were men of the greatest Caution, and Prudence imaginable; most careful in all their words, and actions, of giving the least offence; Men of the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>test Compliance in all indifferent matters, such as stood upon no punctilio's, but yielded to every one, in all things that they could, <hi>becoming all things to all men,</hi> as our great <hi>Apostle</hi> professes of himself; living as <hi>Jewes,</hi> or <hi>Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles,</hi> accordingly as they conversed with them that lived under, or without the Law; although, I say, they were men of such <hi>Free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom</hi> and ingenuity, and could suite them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves with all tempers and dispositions, in all indifferent matters, which was not the least Instance of the excellency of their Spirits: yet in all things of plain duty, where they had the command of God to bear them out, they were Men of the most resolved, and steddy principles, they would endure Tryal
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:63166:15"/>of cruel mockings, and scourgings, of bonds, and imprisonment, and death, rather than they would renounce one tittle of their holy Faith, or be any way drawn from the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formance of their duty. By this did the <hi>Primitive Christians</hi> offer themselves up will<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing sacrifices to their <hi>Heathen</hi> persecutors; and by this did our <hi>Protestant Ancestors</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm the truth of their profession with their bloud. When the <hi>Papists</hi> made bone-fires of such as could not swallow their doctrine of <hi>Transubstantiation;</hi> persecuted them to the death, that could not partake of their <hi>Altar,</hi> where they pretend to sacrifice <hi>Jesus Christ,</hi> i. e. to kill, and destroy him, If the <hi>formal</hi> notion of a <hi>Sacrifice,</hi> as their own men say, lies in the destruction of it; because they could not believe that a <hi>Priest</hi> could make his God, by saying of a few words, and then pay <hi>Divine,</hi> and therefore <hi>Idolaltrical</hi> worship to the <hi>Host;</hi> therefore must they be burnt for <hi>Hereticks;</hi> and so they were indeed, and resolutely lost their lives, rather than they would by any sinful compliances renounce, or dissemble their holy profession; and by that <hi>Heroick</hi> Act, gave signal proof of the va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour and <hi>excellency</hi> of their Spirits.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:63166:16"/>2. A patient and magnanimous bearing of all the Afflictions, and calamities of this life, is the next Instance of this <hi>Excellency</hi> of Spirit.</p>
            <p>For the Illustrating of this, it may not be unworthy our observation, to take notice that the word in the <hi>Text</hi> translated <hi>excellent,</hi> is derived from one signifying to <hi>strengthen an House with beams,</hi> and therefore is applied to him, as a <hi>Learned</hi> man observes, <hi>cujus animus contignatus est, et quasi Immissis trabibus compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctus, h. e. fortis et malorum tolerans. To endure hardship as a good Souldier of Jesus Christ,</hi> not to sink under the pressure of afflictions, but when the <hi>rain descends, the Floods come, the Winds blow, and beat upon him,</hi> then to stand Immoveable, and not to flinch from his foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation, is an argument of a <hi>Firm, Masculine,</hi> and well-composed spirit.</p>
            <p>Now by this enduring of Afflictions, is not meant a stubborn and resolved contempt of them, bearing them without all sense, with such an <hi>apathy</hi> as the <hi>Stoicks,</hi> who used to mis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call things, practised; &amp; by that means lost the opportunity of improving them: But an hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, &amp; cheerful submission to the Divine Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence, which sends that bitter Cup unto us,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:63166:16"/>and will not let it pass away from us, except we drink it; in consideration of the great goodness, and clemency, justice, and Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raignty of Almighty God, that he doth what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soever pleaseth him; that he is righteous in all his wayes; and of very <hi>Faithfulness</hi> caus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth us to be troubled; <hi>and that he doth not af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flict willingly, nor grieve the Children of men,</hi> but upon very good reason, and to some good end, <hi>that we might be partakers of his holiness.</hi> For if they come from him as acts of <hi>Justice,</hi> then it is to chastise us for our former back<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>slidings; to make us remember whence we are fallen, and repent and return unto him; If they are <hi>trials</hi> of our spiritual strength, we see the great esteem that God hath of us, to train us up thus in <hi>Military</hi> discipline; that when he shall require it, we may prove our selves to be <hi>good Souldiers</hi> of Jesus Christ, and by such exercises may be fitted to do, or to suffer any thing for his Name; but if they shall be proper <hi>persecutions,</hi> &amp; be inflicted on us by the contrivance of the <hi>Evil one,</hi> because we will adhere to our God, and to our religion; then are they our <hi>Crown,</hi> and our <hi>Glory;</hi> and under what notion soever they come, to bear them with Christian patience, is a great ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument of <hi>magnanimity,</hi> that is, of an <hi>excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:63166:17"/>Spirit. Magnus es vir, sed unde scio si tibi fortuna non dat Facultatem exhibendae virtutis?</hi> you think that you have a great Spirit, saith <hi>Seneca,</hi> but how does it appear; If your va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour was never tried by sufferings? <hi>Regulus,</hi> saith he, became famous by his torments, it was those which made him such an example of fidelity and patience; <hi>Socrates</hi>'s honour became more conspicuous by his adversaries calumnies; and no man could have known what a great personage <hi>Fabritius</hi> had been, If he had not had poverty to have conflicted with. <hi>Indeed, magnum exemplum nisi mala For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuna non invenit, it is being appointed unto death,</hi> (to translate that in the <hi>Apostles</hi> words) <hi>that must make us a Spectacle to the World, and to An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels, and to Men.</hi> This was the path which our Lord trod before us, he, <hi>for the suffering of death, was crowned with glory, and honour; for it became him, for whom are all things, and by whom are all things, in bringing many Sons unto Glory, to make the Captain of their Salvation per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect through Sufferings.</hi> Heb. 2.10.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The next instance, is a valiant resist<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing all the gay Temptations of the World, when they become motives to draw us into Sin.</p>
            <p>And indeed, this seems an argument of
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:63166:17"/>greater <hi>worth</hi> and <hi>excellency</hi> then the former, in as much as afflictions are apt to make our minds grow strong, and sinewy, make us re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>collect our Forces, stand upon our Guard, and be more watchful to gain such advantages, as may relieve us, and even by frequent re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sisting we get more courage; and so at length frequently obtain the victory. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as the Temptations of the World are apt to loosen, and dissolve our minds, they work upon us insensibly, and before we are aware of them; they have a party within our Breasts, which is ready to prepare their way for them, and to give them entertainment; he that endeavours to study, and understand them, though with a design to resist them, sometimes hazards his Innocence; but he that contracts an acquaintance with them loses it; the best way to save our selves is to <hi>escape</hi> the pollutions of the World; he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quers its Temptations, that flieth from them.</p>
            <p>We have heard of the excellency of <hi>Jo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sephs</hi> Spirit, how by the superabundance of that grace that was given unto him, he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sisted the frequent solicitations of his <hi>Mistress,</hi> though all the comforts of this World, might seem to depend upon his enjoying of the
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:63166:18"/>light of her Countenance; and by subduing his inclinations, and overcoming his interests, making all yield to the Divine command, he shewed himself to be in a good measure fit for the government of <hi>Egypt.</hi> Upon the same principle was it, that <hi>Moses</hi> refused to be called the Son of <hi>Pharaoh</hi>'s daughter, when once he saw that those honours would stand between him, and the Love and ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice of God; and therefore did he despise the pleasures of Sin, and esteem the reproach of <hi>Christ,</hi> greater riches than all the treasures of <hi>Egypt.</hi> And he that can thus overcome the World, and keep his Integrity, when ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, and honours, and pleasures, shall be the reward of his falling down, and wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shiping, must needs be a person of an excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent Spirit.</p>
            <p>The Devil reserved this, for the last onset that he made upon our <hi>Blessed Saviour,</hi> St. Matt. 4.8, 9. <hi>He shewed him all the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms of the World, and the glory of them, and saith unto him, all these things will I give thee, if thou wilt fall down and worship me;</hi> upon whose re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fusal, and sharp rebuke of the impudent Tempter, the <hi>Devil leaveth him,</hi> v. 11. as knowing, that it was to no boot, to solicite
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:63166:18"/>him any longer, who had shewed himself to be all that he pretended, by his despising so great an offer.</p>
            <p>Indeed, when we well consider it, what are all the satisfactions of this World, to the desires, and acquisitions of an excellent mind? what are all those things that men make such a bustle about, for which they will sacrifice their lives, and study, and health, and peace; nay for which they will ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture their Souls, and run the hazard of being damn'd, but straws and feathers, the trifles of Fools, and Children, when compared with the concerns of the other World, and with the Everlasting portion of our under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing Man.</p>
            <p>As <hi>Scipio</hi> was going up to Heaven, <hi>Cicero</hi> tells us (in his <hi>Som. Scip.</hi>) that the whole earth appeared so little to him, <hi>ut me imperij nostri poeniteret,</hi> (saith he;) that he was ashamed of his victories and triumphs, amazed at his madness in Fighting about Kingdomes, which now scarce appeared; and he could not but look down with contempt, upon all the Glory of the World which he had left behind him; <hi>The nearer surely that any one is to Heaven, the less considerable will this World ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear in his Eye.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">
               <pb n="30" facs="tcp:63166:19"/>4. The next instance of this excellent Spirit, is forgiving, and loving of our Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies.</p>
            <p>To see things clearly, and distinctly, and to give unto every one of them their proper esteem, notwithstanding the confusion, and disorder, that they may put themselves into, by their animosities, and ill govern'd pas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sions; to be able to seperate betwixt a mans Sins, and his person; and to pursue this with Love, and those with remedies; not to be prejudiced against an enemy by injuries, and ungrateful dealing; but to see, and love in him, that which is truely amiable, and to do good unto him, for those characters of the <hi>divine Image,</hi> that are yet visible in him; This is indeed to shew our selves to be of <hi>noble,</hi> and <hi>divine</hi> extraction; to be like unto our <hi>Father</hi> which is in <hi>Heaven, who is good un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the unthankful, and to the Evil;</hi> and has therefore commanded us <hi>to love our Enemies, to bless them that curse us, and to pray for them that despightfully use us, and persecute us; that so we may be the Children of our Father which is in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven; and perfect, even as our Father which is in Heaven is perfect.</hi> S. Matt. 6.44. and 48.</p>
            <p>This is the ornament of that <hi>meek</hi> and <hi>qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>et,</hi>
               <pb n="31" facs="tcp:63166:19"/>and <hi>cool</hi> Spirit, which is in the sight of God, of great price. This is the fruit of that <hi>humility,</hi> which the holy doctrine, and example of our <hi>Lord</hi> teacheth us, and to which he hath promised the highest exal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation.</p>
            <p>To the performance of this duty we are obliged, not onely, for the honour and cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit of our religion, whereof this great law of <hi>charity</hi> is by <hi>some</hi> thought to be a <hi>peculiar pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept;</hi> but also by all the <hi>benefits</hi> which we hope to obtain by our <hi>Christianity;</hi> For we can upon no other score expect remission of our Sins at Gods hands, for Christs sake, but even <hi>as we from our hearts forgive, every one our Brother his trespasses.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Put on therefore as the elect of God, holy and beloved, bowels of mercies, kindness, humbleness of mind, meekness, Long-suffering; Forbearing one another, and forgiving one another, If any man have a quarrel against any: even as Christ forgave you, so also do ye. And let all bitter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness, and wrath, and anger, and clamour, and evil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>speaking be put away from you, with all malice.</hi> For indeed to delight in revenge, and to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn spight, and ill-will, for injury, has been alwaies counted an argument of a weak and <hi>Feminine</hi> Spirit;</p>
            <pb n="32" facs="tcp:63166:20"/>
            <p>Such persons may not be satisfied without the ruine of their Enemies; nay, not well pleased unless they may be the Executioners of the mischief; but this is a most hateful temper, such as sets a man at the greatest di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stance from all the kindness and mercy of Heaven, and makes him onely fit for the so<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciety of <hi>Devils,</hi> and <hi>damned Spirits.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">5. The last Instance, is delighting in Universal beneficence, in doing good unto all Men.</p>
            <p>It was the hymn of the <hi>Angels</hi> at the birth of <hi>our Lord,</hi> that <hi>Gods good will towards men,</hi> was <hi>glory to him in the highest,</hi> and <hi>on Earth peace;</hi> and we cannot make Gods glory more illu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strious, then by imitating his good will, in doing of much good unto others. By re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joycing over the happy, and prosperous man, and blessing of God for the good things which our Neighbour enjoys; By relieving the necessities of the poor, liberally, and chearfully; visiting, and comforting the sick; providing for Orphans; redeeming of Prisoners, and captives. Endeavouring by frequent Prayers, by seasonable Councel, by good Example, to bring into the way of Piety, such as are strangers to it; to confirm
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:63166:20"/>and establish those that already walk in it; and by the Spirit of meekness to oppose them that set themselves against it; this is to walk, as we have had our Lord for an Example, <hi>who went about doing good;</hi> This is truly to imitate the divine be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neficence, and to give signal testimony of an <hi>ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent</hi> Spirit.</p>
            <p>God doth much good to all his creatures, meer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly for the sake of the <hi>excellency</hi> of the act of <hi>doing good;</hi> and all things are delightful to him, onely as they imitate, and receive his goodness. By it does he communicate of his fulness with pleasure, and receives the services of his Saints with satis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction: This is the Fountain of all those graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous manifestations which he has made of himself to the World, <hi>wherein he hath abounded towards it in all Wisdom and Prudence;</hi> and not onely his <hi>Eternal Power,</hi> and <hi>Godhead,</hi> but his <hi>goodness</hi> also is <hi>clearly seen by the things that are made,</hi> having made every thing good about us, for our greater, and fuller felicity. It is to this that we must ascribe our Redemption, It is because he is loving unto every Man, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause he takes no pleasure in the death of a Sinner, but delights in shewing mercy which is his great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>est glory, <hi>that he manifested the exceeding great riches of his Grace, in his kindness towards us in Christ Jesus; and sent his Son into the World, that the World through him might be saved.</hi> Finally, it is this Immense
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:63166:21"/>goodness which has prepared for all those that love him in sincerity, <hi>a crown of righteousness, full<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness of joy, and pleasures for evermore.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And if this delighting in <hi>Beneficence</hi> were but the great principle of all our actions, how happy might we make our selves, and all that are about us. This would transform Earth into Paradise, and one man would become instead of God to another. This would remove all envy, and evil-speaking, hatred, and contention out of the World, it would lay the axe to that root of bitterness, whence spring slanders, and back-bitings, <hi>duels,</hi> and <hi>fightings;</hi> and would introduce into it, peace, and bounty, order, and harmony, joy unspeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able and full of glory. This would declare us to <hi>be the Children of the highest,</hi> when we can <hi>do good,</hi> and <hi>lend</hi> (as our Lord commands us) <hi>hoping for no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing again;</hi> even when our doing good may some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times interfere with our secular interests; this in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed manifests the true excellency of Spirit.</p>
            <p>I come now to the last thing I proposed to speak unto, namely to shew briefly,</p>
            <p n="3">3. How this Divine Wisdom contributes to the <hi>Ennobling</hi> of the mind, so as to make a man in whom it resides, be <hi>Emphatically</hi> called one of an <hi>excellent spirit.</hi> And this it does in these following Parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culars.</p>
            <p n="1">1. By inlightning the Mind, and informing it
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:63166:21"/>with the knowledg of the best, and most excellent things.</p>
            <p n="2">2. By regulating and governing the affections of our Minds.</p>
            <p n="3">3. By bringing peace and tranquility to our Minds, giving them that ease and satisfaction with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out which no man can have a great and <hi>Excellent spirit.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. By teaching us to improve the excellency of most humane actions.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Divine Wisdom helps to <hi>exalt</hi> and <hi>ennoble</hi> our Minds, and to form <hi>excellent</hi> spirits within us, by inlightning our understandings, and informing us with the knowledg of the best and most excellent things.</p>
            <p>For so much more darkness as is upon our Minds, so much more shall we be prone to Errour, and <hi>Superstition;</hi> which will cause disorder, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fusion in our actions, inconstancy in our resolutions; which will employ our Minds about little affairs, unworthy of their dignity; will make us shoot under that noble Mark to which we should direct them, and beget a great lowness, and degeneracy of spirit in us. But now <hi>when Wisdom entreth into thine heart, and Knowledg is pleasant to thy Soul, Dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretion shall preserve thee, Understanding shall keep thee, and deliver thee from the way of the evil man.</hi> This will enlarge thy Understanding, enable it to see beyond
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:63166:22"/>the narrow bounds of time and sense, to behold things that are invisible, to <hi>look within the vail, whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the Fore-runner is for us entred,</hi> and to know him that passeth all knowledge. And then thou wilt find thy feet set in <hi>a large room,</hi> and that thou canst run the way of Gods Commandments, when he has thus enlarged thy heart, with the knowledge of the most useful, and excellent things. For such they are, which this Divine Wisdom teacheth us. For it clearly reveals to us, the noblest end unto which we can aspire, namely the attainment of that <hi>life and Immortality,</hi> which our Lord purcha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed for all those that obey him; and furnisheth us with the true means that will qualifie us for it, and conduct us to it; by teaching us to be <hi>like unto God,</hi> by our living up to the dignity of our rational Natures, and of our holy profession.</p>
            <p n="2">2. By regulating and governing the affections of our Mind.</p>
            <p>The <hi>affections</hi> are not unfitly styled by some, <hi>the Wings and Chariot of the Soul;</hi> For by them is the Soul carried forth towards those objects which de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light it, with joy, and briskness; and flyes those which it has an <hi>aversion</hi> for, with eagerness: Now when the affections are disorderly and Immode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate, the Soul is driven by them as the <hi>Chariot</hi> of the <hi>Sun</hi> is said to have bin by <hi>Phaeton,</hi> out of its proper road, into dangerous untrodden paths, to
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:63166:22"/>the manifest hazard of the Rider; or as <hi>Ships</hi> in the Sea that are driven by fierce Winds, and want a Prudent <hi>Governour</hi> at the Helm, whithersoever the wind listeth. The irregularity of the passions nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row and contract the Mind, brings it into straits, and difficulties, weakens its <hi>cognoscitive</hi> and <hi>motive</hi> Faculties, makes it unfit to discern, and unable to perform its several offices. But now this <hi>Wisdom</hi> introduceth <hi>light</hi> and <hi>order</hi> among the affections, by setting every one of them about their proper work, prescribing to them their due bounds, saying un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to each of them, <hi>Hitherto shalt thou come, and no further.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This refines and sublimates our <hi>Love,</hi> it teacheth us what, and how far we should love, by giving us clear and distinct Notions of every object's loveli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness; and so informeth us, what kind, and degree of affection we should bestow upon the things of <hi>this life;</hi> and with what zeal, and ardour we should pursue those which concern the <hi>next.</hi> This discovers what Foundation we may have for a <hi>sure</hi> and <hi>stedfast Hope;</hi> or what ground for a <hi>discreet</hi> and <hi>rational Fear;</hi> what bottom we may lay for a <hi>lasting joy;</hi> and how we may make <hi>sorrow,</hi> and <hi>heaviness</hi> flee away. In <hi>summ,</hi> it teacheth us how we may make all our <hi>Passions</hi> instruments of Religion and Virtue, and so <hi>spiritualize,</hi> and ennoble even the <hi>inferiour Faculties</hi> of the Soul, make them fit, and
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:63166:23"/>ready for every good work, and highly serviceable to the <hi>superiour,</hi> and more spiritual <hi>powers</hi> of the Mind; and consequently must needs add much to the Excellency of the spirit. Which this Wisdom does further promote</p>
            <p n="3">3. By bringing <hi>Peace</hi> and Tranquility to our Minds, giving them that ease and satisfaction with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out which no man can have a great and <hi>Excellent</hi> spirit.</p>
            <p>For when the Mind is not at ease, when all is not <hi>peace</hi> within, but the storms which arise there <hi>ruffle</hi> it, and put it out of its own posture; this must needs hinder its <hi>true Magnanimity,</hi> and make it Cowardly, and <hi>Superstitious;</hi> apt to suspect the worst that can happen, and yet unable to provide against it, or to sustain it when it does come. <hi>The wicked flee</hi> (saith the <hi>Wise Man) when no man pursueth, but the Righteous are as bold as a Lion. Those</hi> are jealous of every evil that may fall out; for they look within themselves, and find nothing but <hi>darkness,</hi> and <hi>dimness of anguish;</hi> but the <hi>other</hi> know not how to be apprehensive of danger, since they see nothing in themselves whence it may arise. An instance of <hi>those,</hi> is <hi>Cain,</hi> who became a <hi>Vagabond</hi> upon the Earth, afraid lest every one that met him would slay him; and of <hi>these,</hi> are they that could say, <hi>We will not fear tho the Earth be removed, tho the Mountains be carried into the midst of the Sea,</hi> Psal. 46.2. or as <hi>David, tho I walk
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:63166:23"/>through the valley of the shadow of death, I will fear no evil,</hi> Ps. 23.4.</p>
            <p>Now it is the property of this <hi>Wisdom,</hi> which is first <hi>pure,</hi> and then <hi>peaceable,</hi> to bring ease and quiet to our Minds. This gives us an account of our Estates from judgment, and certainty, and not from conjecture and fancy. It informs us truly what we are, and tells us also what we may be; that we are born to high and mighty things; that we are made capable of great honours, and vast Inheritances, and everlasting Pleasures, such as shall not wast them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves in the enjoyment, nor ever cloy us, tho we shall live to Eternity upon them; and this is apt to create joy and delight in our Minds, and conse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently to exalt and raise our spirits. Which this Divine Wisdom doth</p>
            <p n="4">4. Lastly, by teaching us to improve the worth of most humane actions, and as a <hi>Wise</hi> Man of our <hi>own</hi> has well observed, instructs us to raise them to a higher pitch of Excellency than of their own Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture they are capable.</p>
            <p>For this teaches us to serve God by the works of our ordinary Callings, by using strict Justice in all our dealings; by referring the success of all our labours to his blessing, and giving God the glory of all our prosperity. By taking the disappointment, and miscarriage of our works, and designs, patient<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and waiting his good pleasure, and his own
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:63166:24"/>time, for better success. By making us industrious and diligent in our several Vocations, yet free from that solicitude and care of the issue of our affairs, which would disturb our repose, and hinder our Souls from enjoying the good, and sweet, of all the labour, and travel which we have taken under the Sun. This will keep the Wisdom of the <hi>Politician</hi> from degenerating into Cunning; it will bottom it upon the firm Principles of Honesty and Integri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and teach him to acknowledge him in all his wayes, who takes the wise in his own craftiness. And Finally, it will teach us all so to use this World, as not abusing it, and so to husband our Portion in this life, that at the Great Day of Accounts, our Lord may say to every one of us, <hi>Well done good and faithful Servant, thou hast been faithful over a few things, I will make thee Ruler over many things, enter thou in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the joy of thy Lord,</hi> To whom with the Father, and the Holy Ghost, Three Persons, and One God, be ascribed by us, and his whole Church, all Praise and Adoration both now, and for evermore, <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>ERRATA.</head>
            <p>PA<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. 2. Line. 21. read, <hi>become.</hi> p. 9. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>1. r. <hi>be.</hi> p. 12. l. 5. r. <hi>religious.</hi> p. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>3. l. 24 r. <hi>he.</hi> p. 16. l. 11. r. <hi>these.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:63166:24"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>